Guide to the Richard Bruce Nugent Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Bruce Nugent papers
1906-2009
JWJ MSS 92
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
22.07
(104 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, personal and financial papers, subject files, photographs, printed materials, and audiovisual materials. Bruce Nugent's correspondence consists of family, professional, and personal correspondence, including letters from homosexual love interests. Writings include poetry, short non-fiction pieces, and various fiction pieces, including the novel Gentleman Jigger. Writings by others include drafts and papers relating to Gay Rebel of the Harlem Renaissance by Thomas H. Wirth. Photographs consist of portraits and snapshots of Nugent, his love interests, friends, and family. The bulk of the audiovisual materials consist of interviews with Nugent. Printed materials include books inscribed to Nugent as well as various clippings and ephemera.
Nugent, Bruce, circa 1880s-1987
Wirth, Thomas H., 1938-2014
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Thomas H. Wirth on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 95 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 102: Restricted until January 1, 2037. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Bruce Nugent
Richard Bruce Nugent was a gay African American writer and painter associated with the Harlem Renaissance.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, personal and financial papers, subject files, photographs, printed materials, and audiovisual materials. Bruce Nugent's correspondence consists of family, professional, and personal correspondence, including letters from homosexual love interests. Writings include poetry, short non-fiction pieces, and various fiction pieces, including the novel Gentleman Jigger. Writings by others include drafts and papers relating to Gay Rebel of the Harlem Renaissance by Thomas H. Wirth. Photographs consist of portraits and snapshots of Nugent, his love interests, friends, and family. The bulk of the audiovisual materials consist of interviews with Nugent. Printed materials include books inscribed to Nugent as well as various clippings and ephemera.
Arrangement
Organized into fourteen series: Series I. Correspondence, 1941-1987. Series II. Poems, short works of fiction and nonfiction, interviews, 1920s-1985. Series III. Long works of fiction, novels, 1929-1985. Series IV. Documentation of Nugent's career, 1927-2009. Series V. Personal, family, and finanical papers, 1906-1990. Series VI. Printed appearances of writings and art by Nugent, 1925-2009. Series VII. Drafts of and correspondence relating to posthumously published work by Nugent, 1995-2007. Series VIII. Writings by others about Nugent, 1983-2009. Series IX. Third-party correspondence, 1946-2008. Series X. Subject files, 1927-1986. Series XI. Photographs, 1880s-1986. Series XII. Books, 1931-1994. Series XIII. Audiovisual materials, 1983-1987. Series XIV. Oversize materials and miscellaneous papers, 1928-2002.
African American authors; African American gays; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; American literature -- 20th Century; Gay men -- 20th Century -- Archives; Harlem Renaissance; Photographs; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Nugent, Bruce, 1906-1987
- Correspondence, 1941-1987; Series I; (17 boxes)
  - Aaronoff, Herman (Chaim), 1964 - 1977; 27 letters; 1 mailgram; 1 clipping (Box 1)
  - Aaronoff, Herman (Chaim), 1977; 15 letters; 4 mailgrams; 1 magazine (Box 1)
  - Aaronoff, Herman (Chaim), 1978-1984, n.d.; To: 22 letters, 5 mailgrams, 1 card, 1 ANS / From: 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Abrams, Bessie, 1947; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Albanese, Frank, 4/7/1961; 1 Letter (Box 1)
    General note
    Proprietor, Frank's Grocery (Bronx)
  - Allen, Jeanne, 1971; 1 letter (Box 1)
  - Amerman, Nick, 1951; 1 letter (Box 1)
    (Amerman was a soldier stationed at Fort Leonard Wood in Missouri.)
  - Anacostia Neighborhood Museum, 1983; 1 Letter (Box 2)
  - Arnstein, Benjamin, 1974-1986; 1 Letter; 1 Postcard (Box 2)
    (Arnstein was a prosperous jeweler in NYC and the husband of Daphne Arnstein.
  - Arnstein, Daphne, 1972-1987; 17 Postcards; 2 Cards (Box 2)
    (Daphne Arnstein was, like Nugent, a member of the board of the Harlem Cultural Council. She was closely associated with Jazzmobile.)
  - Arnstein, Daphne, 1969-1983; 19 Letters; 1 Envelope (Box 2)
  - Auzenne, Edward A., 1948-1949; 3 Letters, 1 Postcard (Box 2)
  - Bader Brothers Warehouses, 1974; 1 Letter (3 copies) (Box 2)
  - Barri, Robert, 1951-1985; 7 Letters; 17 Postcards; 1 Card (Box 2)
  - Barrow, Muriel Ives, 1952; 1 Letters; 1 Card; 1 Envelope (Box 2)
    Muriel Ives Barrow Newhall was the daughter of Howard Colby Ives, a prominent early American disciple of the Baha'i faith. Mrs. Newhall is the author of Mother's Stories: Recollections of Abdu'l-Baha (1970)
  - Barthe, Richmond, ca 1962-1981; 4 Letters; 17 Postcards; 8 Cards (Box 2)
  - Barthe, Richmond, 1971-1973; 12 Letters (Box 2)
    From Florence
  - Barthe, Richmond, 1977-1983; 7 Letters; 1 Card (Box 2)
  - Barthe, Richmond, 1971; 1 Letter with enclosures (Box 2)
    Enclosed; 2 newspaper clippings (Langston Hughes, Kenneth MacPherson) 2 small photographs of Barthe in Florence
  - Barthe, Richmond, 1985; 1 Letter with enclosures (Box 2)
  - Barthe, Richmond, 1982-ca 1985; 2 Letters (Box 2)
    Letters from Nugent to Barthe (presmably unsent)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation -- David Perry, 1982; 1 Letter (Box 3)
  - Beam, Joseph, 1985-1986; 3 Letters (with enclosures) (Box 3)
    Enclosures include a 16-page typescript of Nugent's interview with Charles Michael Smith that appeared in Beam's anthology In The Life (Alyson, 1986) with revisions dated "1/17
  - Bearden, Romare, 1969-1972; 2 Letters (Box 3)
  - Before Stonewall (Greta Schiller, Neil Miller, Jewelle Gomez, Robbie --?---, 1983-1985; 6 Letters, 2 Postcards, Enclosures (Box 3)
  - Berry, Faith, 1977-1986; 5 Items, Enclosures (Box 3)
    Includes a Xerox copy of "Black Poets, White Patrons: The Harlem Renaissance Years of Langston Hughes" (Crisis, July 1981)
  - Betti, Silvio, 1985-1986; 3 Items (Box 3)
    Betti is an Italian artist
  - Bhalla, Hans, 1967; 1 Letter (Box 3)
    Retained carbon of letter by Nugent
  - Billops, Camille, 1 Postcard (Box 3)
    Billops, a well-respected artist, is the wife of James Hatch and co-founder of the Hatch-Billops Collection, a black cultural archive.
  - Board of Elections, 1957-1970; 2 Postcards, 1 Card (Box 3)
  - Boseley, Roberta, 1945; 1 Letter (Box 3)
  - Bremen, Paul, 1958; 1 Letter (Box 3)
    Paul Bremen was the Dutch publisher of the "Heritage Series" of poetry chapbooks.
  - Bundles, A'Lelia, 1983-1986; 6 Letters, 3 Postcards, 2 Cards (Box 3)
    Bundles is the great-granddaughter of Madame C. J. Walker and the author of her biography.
  - Burkel, Fred, 1972; 1 Letter (Box 3)
  - Center, M'em (?), 1946; 1 Letter with enclosure (Box 3)
  - Coates, Paul, 1983; 1 Letter, with several enclosures (Box 3)
    The enclosures relate to the Moorland-Spingarn Collection at Howard University
  - Cole, Margaret, 1979-1987; 3 Letters, 5 Cards, 2 Empty Envelopes (Box 3)
    Cole is Nugent's cousin (the daughter of his father's sister.)
  - Creevey, Emily, 1969; 1 Letter (Box 3)
  - Criselle, Lisa, 1975-1977; 2 Letters, 3 Cards, 1 Enclosed Photo (Box 3)
    Small photo of Criselle
  - Cumbo, Clarissa, 1 Letter (Box 3)
  - Cuney, Waring, 1972-1975; 2 Letters, 2 Cards, 1 Clipping (Box 3)
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio, 1971-1979; 63 Letters, 13 Postcards, 8 Cards (Box 4)
    Letters in Italian from D'Ambrosio, who was Nugent's great love in the 1970s. Arranged In chronological order by Nugent.
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio, 1971-1979; 64 Envelopes (empty) (Box 4)
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio--Letters from Nugent, 1971-1979; Numerous Items (Box 4)
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio--Letters from Nugent, 1971-1979; Numerous Items (Box 4)
    Includes letters and fragments in English, many with Italian translations, either separate or interlinear, as well as some items in Italian. Disorganized.
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio--Fragments for, 1972-1979; Numerous Items (Box 5)
    Fragments in English & Italian written by Nugent for D'Ambrosio
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio--Contract, ca 1976; Several Items (Box 5)
    Contract relating to the production of a Nugent invention. Versions in English & Italian with explanatory notes.
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio--Notebook, 1 Notebook (Box 5)
    Notebook for Italian class, with several letters to D'Ambrosio written out for interlinear translation.
  - D'Ambrosio, Antonio--Pages from a Notebook, 1 Notebook (Box 5)
    Notebook with several letters to D'Ambrosio written out for interlinear translation into Italian.
  - Daroda, Mirella, 1975; 1 Letter with enclosed newspaper clipping (Box 5)
    The newspaper clipping includes a photo of Nugent at a party in Rome.
  - Davis, Thadious, 1983; 2 Letters (Box 5)
  - De Castro, Luis, 1947; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    Letter in spanish, with sheet of penciled translation notes
  - Dernini, Allesandro, 1986-1987; 3 Postcards, 1 Calling Card, 1 Photo (Box 5)
  - DeSola, Carla, 1 Postcard (Box 5)
    Change of address card. Carla DeSola, a liturgical dancer and choreographer, is the daughter of Helen Winner DeSola. She founded and directs the Omega West Dance Company in San Francisco.
  - DeSola, Helen Winner, 1970-1986; 9 Letters, 5 Cards, 2 Postcards (Box 5)
  - diBiccari, Evelyn, 1945; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    Evelyn diBiccari was the wife of the Boston-based sculptor Adio diBiccari. The letter contains a short poem by her.
  - Diggins, 1929; 1 Postcard (Box 5)
    (England, Porgy tour)
  - Dodson, Owen, 1983; 1 Card (Box 5)
    Funeral invitation
  - Duff, S.K., 1985; 1 Envelope (Box 5)
    Empty envelope
  - Dyle, ---, 1976; 1 Card (Box 5)
    Christmas card, with photo & reference to Tanglewood '75
  - Eddy, Burton, 1 Postcard (Box 5)
  - England, Paul, 1983-1988; 1 Letter, 4 Cards (Box 6)
    England was a well-known artist. The letter, announcing his death in 1988, was sent to THW from England's sister.
  - English, Walter, 1974-1987; 5 Letters (with enclosures), 1 Card (Box 6)
    English was RBN's cousin, the son of Nugent's maternal aunt Mabel Bruce English
  - Ferranti, Ben, 1943-1945; 12 Letters, 1 Postcard (Box 6)
    Ferranti was a soldier.
  - Fierst, A. L., 1950; 1 Letter (Box 6)
    Fierst is a literary agent
  - Fine Arts Federation of New York, 1971-1986; 22 Letters (Box 6)
    Mostly meeting notices, minutes, etc
  - FIRE II, 1983-1984; 2 Letters, 2 Cards (Box 6)
    FIRE II is a student publication at Trenton State University. (See subject file for two issues.)
  - Frankel, H, 1949; 1 Item (Box 6)
  - Franco, Joseph R. (Jose), 1946; 4 Items (Box 6)
    2 Letters in Spanish, 1 Envelope, 1 Postcard. Franco was in the Navy.
  - Freeman, Wilbur, 1944-1948; 11 Items (Box 6)
    Freeman was a soldier. For his photo, see the photo files.
  - G------, H------, ca 1941; 1 Letter (Box 6)
    Unsent letter from "Boss" (RBN) to "H. G." on the letterhead of "Daybreak House." The letterhead was designed by Nugent; the design is dated 1940
  - Garber, Eric, 1981-1985; 21 Letters, 8 Cards, 3 Empty Envelopes (Box 6)
    One of the letters is the first page of an unsent letter from Nugent to Garber. Eric Garber was a young gay scholar interested in the Harlem Renaissance.
  - Garber, Eric (Perez Family), 1 Letter (Box 6)
    Unsent (?) letter, to Eric Garber, ribbon copy, narrating RBN's relationship with the Perez family, with an explicit discussion of his sexual relationships with several of the Perez brothers--Sammy, Angelo, Jerry, & Jessie (Jesus).
  - Giard, Robert, 1987; 1 Letter (Box 6)
    Giard was a well-regarded portrait photographer.
  - Gibson, Roland, 1971; 1 Letter (Box 6)
  - Gicoliyzi, Stefane, 1948; 1 Letter (Box 6)
  - Giordano, George, 1941-1947; 4 Letters, 1 Empty Envelope, 3 Postcards (Box 6)
  - Goffe, Lewis C., 1978; 10 Items (Misc) (Box 7)
    Goffe, on the faculty of the University of New Hampshire, taped interviews with RBN, for which RBN was paid.
  - Govan, Sandra Y., 1982; 2 Letters (Box 7)
  - Greaves, William, 1976; 4 Misc (Box 7)
  - Hahn, Hannelore, 1983; 1 Invitation (Box 7)
  - Hart, Ted, 1952; 1 Letter (Box 7)
    Hart was a composer, and, judging from the letter, gay
  - Hawkins, Clymenza, 1983; 1 Typescript of an Aritcle about RBN (Box 7)
    36pp typescript
  - Haynes, Olyve Jeter, 1973-1981; 1 Postcard, 1 Card, 1 Letter (Box 7)
  - Heins, Barbara, 1984; 1 Letter (Box 7)
  - Hemenway, Robert, 1971; 1 Letter (Box 7)
  - Hoerner, Barbara, 1982-1987; 3 Cards (Box 7)
  - Hofstra University, 1984; 1 Letter (Box 7)
  - Horwood, Mary Fair Williams, 1983; 1 Card, 1 Note with enclosures (Box 7)
  - Hueckers, Ann, 1983; 1 Christmas Card (Box 7)
  - Hurston, Zora Neale, 1944; Short holograph note (Box 7)
  - Izquierdo, Mrs. Pedor A, n.d.; 1 Letter (Box 7)
    Addressed to Grace & Bruce. Delivered by hand prior to their return to the US from Puerto Rico. Reference to Dorothy & Sidney [Peterson]. Receipes enclosed.
  - Jackson, David, 1984; 1 Letter (Box 7)
    Chain letter
  - Jackman, Harold, 1961; 1 Leaf (Box 7)
    Letter about Alexander Gumby's estate. Nugent & Jackman acted as co-executors.
  - Jambi, J., 1986; 1 Postcard (Box 7)
  - Jenkins, Raymond, 1974-1986; 4 Letters, 2 Christmas Cards, 2 Postcards, 1 Envelope (Box 7)
    Jenkins, an artist who worked as a draftsman for the City of New York, met Nugent in the 1930s and was one of Nugent's very best friends in Nugent's later years.
  - Jennings, Corrine, 1984; 1 Letter with Enclosure (Box 7)
    Enclosure is a copy of an article by Lionel Mitchell from the Amsterdam News in which Nugent is mentioned
  - Jeter, William [Clark], 1975-1979; 1 Card, 1 Christmas Card (Box 7)
  - John, Alma Vessels, 1948; 1 Letter (Box 7)
  - Johnson, Georgia Douglas (1), 1946; 1 Letter with Enclosures (Box 8)
    Enclosed is the sheet music (dittoed, 2pp.) of "Bortherhood Marching Song" with words & music by GDJ. GDJ was an important African American poet.
  - Johnson, Georgia Douglas (2), 1947; 1 Letter with Enclosures (Box 8)
    Enclosed is a carbon copy of the introduction (by Cedric Dover) and table of contents to "After a Thousand Tears," an unpublished volume of verse by GDJ.
  - Johnson, Georgis Douglas (3), 1947-1952; 6 Letters (Box 8)
  - Johnson, Helen Armstead, 1985-1987; 1 Letter, 1 Get-Well Card (Box 8)
    Refers to John Rucker, blackface vaudeville performer, who was married to one of Nugent's aunts (on his mother's side). Helen Armstead Johnson was a collector of African-American theatrical memorabilia.
  - Johnson, Henry Lincoln, 1965; 2 Letters (Box 8)
    Refers to the estate of Mabel English, Nugent's aunt (on his mother's side). Henry Lincoln Johnson was an attorney and son of Georgia Douglas Johnson.
  - Kagawa Family, 2 Christmas Cards (Box 8)
  - Kapslis, Mary, 1949-1977; 19 Letters (Box 8)
  - Karp, Ira, 1 Christmas Card (Box 8)
  - Kay, Bernard [aka "Machiavelli"; Philip Drury], 1947-1978; 4 Letters, 5 Postcards, 1 Christmas Card, 1 Invitation (Box 8)
  - Keeling, Rai, 1974; 3 Letters (Box 8)
  - Kellner, Bruce, 1982-1986; 10 Letters, 6 Postcards, 1 Envelope, Enclosures (Box 8)
    Enclosures include a typescript of "Carl Van Vechten's Black Renaissance" (13 pp) and "A Sonnet for Richard Bruce Nugent on the Occasion of His Eightieth Birthday
  - King, Woodie, 1983; 1 Letter (Box 9)
  - Klotz, Mary, 1986; 1 Letter with Enclosure (Box 9)
    The enclosure is an obituary of Krishnamurti.
  - Krysko, Steve, 1987; 1 Get Well Card (Box 9)
  - LaFrance, Fred, 1944-1945; 4 (Box 100)
  - LaFrance, Fred, 1945-1987, undated; 7 (Box 101)
  - Landau, Seymour, 1949-1952; 9 Letters, 36 Postcards, 1 Business Card (Box 9)
    Landau was a college student at the University of Connecticut, Storrs, who apparently then entered the army. He later became an attorney.
  - Landlords, 1965-1979; 18 Irems (Box 9)
    150 Nassau St & 99-101 Beekman St
  - Lane, Pinkie Gordon, 1985; 1 Letter (Box 9)
    Lane is an African American poet.
  - Langston Hughes Society, 2 Letters (Box 9)
  - Laroche, Julia English, 1973-1982; "7 Letters " (Box 9)
    Julia Laroche (Mrs. Roche B. Laroche) was Nugent's cousin--the daughter of his maternal aunt Mabel Bruce English
  - Larson, Charles R., 1985; 1 Letter (Box 9)
  - Lewis, David Levering, 1974-1983; 4 Letters, 1 Postcard, 3 Christmas Cards (Box 9)
  - Linfante, Chuck, 1967; 2 Letters (Box 9)
  - Linfante, Florence, 1971; 1 Letter (Box 9)
  - Linfante, Mary Ellen, 1976-1977; 3 Letters, 2 Christmas Cards (Box 9)
  - Liraf, Damt (?), 1962; 1 Letter with Enclosed Clippings (Box 9)
  - Lunenfeld, Sgt. Murray, 1943-1944; 2 Postcards (Box 9)
  - Marino, Silvio, 1943; 1 Letter (Box 9)
  - Marr, Carmel, 1981; 1 Letter, 1 Envelope (Box 10)
    Carmel Marr is the wifej of Warren Marr II--Nugent's brother-in-law. She was a Republican attorney and member of the New York State Public Service Commission
  - Marr, Charles, 1944-1946; 4 Letters (Box 10)
    Charles Marr was the brother of Nugent's wife, Grace Marr
  - Marr, Grace, 1948-1965; 19 Letters, 4 Postcards, 1 Envelope, 1 Holograph Poem (Box 10)
    Enclosed in one letter is a prospectus for "Operation Democracy
  - Marr, Grace-Condolances, 1970; 4 Letters (Box 10)
  - Marr, James, 1986; 1 Letter (Box 10)
    James Marr was one of the brothers of Grace Marr
  - Marr, Warren, Sr., 1947; 2 Letters, 1 Carbon Copy of a Response (Box 10)
  - Marr II, Warren, 1966-1986; 2 Letters, 1 Note, 3 Cards, 1 Carbon of RBN Letter to Marr (Box 10)
  - Marrese, Nicholas ("Flash"; "F"), 1940-1945; ca 47 Letters,1 Book of Postcards, 7 "V-Letters" [Photostats], 7 Cards, 2 Notes, 3 Fragments (Box 10)
    Marrese was one of Nugent's major romantic interests. Most of the letters, which were removed from their envelopes, are dated in Nugent's hand.
  - Martino, J. A.Torres, 1962; 1 Letter (Box 10)
    Martino is a Puerto Rican artist.
  - Mason, E. Harold, 1961-1977; 7 Letters, 4 Cards, Enclosures (Box 10)
    Enclosed are clippings about a performance of "Sahdji" in Los Angeles.
  - Mayo, George, 1973-1986; 8 Letters, 11 Cards, 1 Envelope (Box 11)
  - Mazey, Ann (Mrs. Lawrence), 1972-1974; 22 Letters, 2 Cards (Box 11)
  - McCluskey, John, 1985; 1 Letter (Box 11)
  - McCurry, -------, 1948; 1 Postcard (Box 11)
  - McDowell, Mary, 1981-1985; 3 Letters, 2 Cards, 2 Envelopes (Box 11)
  - McQueen, Njambi, 1986; 1 Letter (Box 11)
  - Men of All Colors Together/New York, 1 Letter with Enclosures, 1 Card, 1 Envelope (Box 11)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 4 Letters, 3 Memoranda, 1 Related Document (Box 11)
    Correspondence concerning an exhibition of work by Black artists to be organized by Nugent, which was cancelled for lack of response from artists.
  - Meyer, Kenneth E., 1958; 1 Letter (Box 11)
  - Miranda, Angel, 1961-1962; 16 Letters, 3 Cards, 1 Envelope (Box 11)
    Miranda was a serviceman.
  - Miscellaneous Envelopes & Cards, 1944-1982; 17 Items (Box 11)
  - Mitchell, Arthur, 1 Note (Box 11)
  - Monson, Lex, 1972-1974; 3 Letters, 4 Cards, 1 Envelope (Box 11)
    Monson (1926-2004) was an African American actor. The letters have explicit homosexual content.
  - Montefore Toledo, Mario ( "M"), 1945-46, 1950; 12 Letters (Box 11)
  - Morelli, Joseph ("Joe"), 1944; 1 Postcard (Box 12)
  - Moses, William Henry, 1983; 1 Letter (Box 12)
    Enclosures
  - Muscle Sculpture Magazine, 1957; 1 Letter (Box 12)
  - Nagano, S., 1961; 1 Letter (Box 12)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1979; 1 Letter (Box 12)
  - Nevel, Ann, 1977; 1 Letter (Box 12)
  - Njambi, 1 Card (Box 12)
  - Nugent, Pauline Minerva Bruce (Williams), 1943-1945; 3 Letters (Box 12)
    Pauline Williams was Nugent's mother. The letters are very revealing of their relationship.
  - Nugent, Gary Lambert ( "Pete"), 1942-1972; 16 Letters, 4 Cards (Box 12)
    Pete Nugent was RBN's younger brother--a well known "hoofer" (tap dancer). In the 1930s he was a member of the trio "Pete, Peaches and Duke," a "class act." During WWII he performed in "This is the Army"
  - Nugent, Gary Lambert ("Pete"), 1947; 1 Letter with enclosure (Box 12)
    Enclosed is a souvenir program of a show in Chicago headlining Sarah Vaughn in which Pete Nugent performed.
  - Nurse, Karl, 1983; 1 Letter (Box 12)
    Letterhead of WCVB TV Boston
  - Other Countries, 1987; 1 Letter, 1 Card (Box 12)
  - Pace, Louis, 1947; 1 Letter (Box 12)
  - Paparchontis, Constantin (Gus Papas), 1974-1976; 9 Letters, 3 Cards, 1 Envelope (Box 12)
  - Patterson, Benjamin, 1984; 1 Invitation (Box 12)
  - Patterson, Louise Thompson, ca 1985; 1 Card (Box 12)
    Patterson was the wife of WallaceThurman and for a time secretary to Langston Hughes
  - Paul, Louise, 1950; 1 Letter (Box 12)
    Louise Paul was a Canadian sculptor who was close friends with Nugent for a time in the 1940s.
  - Perez, Angelo, 1960-1977; 3 Letters, 4 Cards, 1 Note (Box 12)
    Angelo Perez was one of Nugent's serious romantic interests.
  - Perez, Grace (Mrs. Lou Rodriguez), 1976-1985; 10 Cards, 1 Wedding Invitation (Box 12)
    Grace Perez is the sister of Angelo, Jerry, Sammy & Jesse Perez
  - Perez, Jerry & Cecilia, 1977-1986; 4 Letters, 9 Cards, 2 Envelopes (Box 12)
    Jerry Perez is the brother of Angelo, Jesse, Sammy & Grace Perez
  - Perez, Jesse, 1977; 1 Card, 1 Wedding Invitation (Box 12)
    Jesse Perez is the brother of Angelo, Jerry, Sammy, & Grace Perez
  - Perez, Providencia, 1977; 1 Card (Box 12)
    Providencia Perez is the mother of Angelo, Jerry, Sammy, Jesse & Grace Perez
  - Perez, Sammy, 1958-1963; 3 Letters, 1 Envelope (Box 12)
    Sammy is the brother of Angelo, Jerry, Jesse & Grace Perez
  - Peterson, Charles, 1944; 2 Letters (Box 13)
  - Pozo, Fermin ("Chino"), 1959; 1 Card (Box 13)
  - Rampersad, Arnold, 1980-1985; 5 Letters (Box 13)
  - Ratliff, Autry Davis, 1982-1986; 3 Flyers, 1 Envelope (Box 13)
  - Reich, Mrs. E. D. ("Barbara"), 1942; 1 Letter (Box 13)
  - Reid, Ira De A., 1945; 1 Letter (Box 13)
    Phylon letterhead. Reid was editor of Phylon.
  - Reid, Margaret, 1983; 1 Letter with Enclosure (Box 13)
    Enclosure: manuscript of "Chapter IV. Rhetorical Analysis of Selected Black Protest Poetry of the Harlem Renaissance" (76 pp)
  - Reidlinger, Vera (Mrs. Wallace F.), 1969-1973; 5 Letters, 1 Card (Box 13)
  - Retrieslika, 1 Letter (Box 13)
  - Ried, Jimmy, 1970, 1972; 1 Letter, 1 Postcard (Box 13)
  - Riley, Jay ("Sandy"), 1972; 3 Letters (Box 13)
    Explicit homosexual content. Riley was a distinguishen African Americana actor and producer.
  - Rivera, Louis, 1948; 1 Letter (Box 13)
  - Robinson, Henry, 1972-1986; 1 Letter, 9 Cards (some dupes), 2 Envelopes (Box 13)
    Robinson was a historian at Morgan State University and a distant cousin on the Bruce side of Nugent's family
  - Roditi, Edouard, 1986; 1 Card (Box 13)
    Roditi was a gay, avant-garde writer & poet who has a brief affair with Nugent in the early 1930s.
  - Roerich, William, 3 Letters (Box 13)
    Roerich was an actor and friend of Pete Nugent & E.M. Forster. He was in the cast of This is the Army.
  - Rosmini, John (Giovanni), 1974; 1 Envelope (Box 13)
  - Rothschild, Manuela, 1 Card (Box 13)
    Unsent sympathy card with a message from Nugent.
  - Sahmen, Zanuel, 1951; 1 Letter (Box 13)
  - Sanabria, Jesus, 1982-1983; 15 Letters, 3 Letters (xerox copies) (Box 13)
    Sanabria was a young friend of Nugent's in Hoboken. During the period of the correspondence, Sanabria was incarcerated.
  - Sanabria, Jesus, 1982-1983; 3 Letters, 2 Cards (Box 13)
    Letters & cards from Nugent to Sanabria
  - Schenck, Sidney, 1983-1984; 1 Card, 1 Invitation (Box 13)
  - Schlick, Robert, 1942-1948; 5 Letters, 1 Invitation (Box 13)